soft engineering radio episode 106
introduction to aspect-oriented
programming this is software engineering
radio the podcast for professional
developers on the web at s e - radio
dotnet se radio prints irrelevant and
detailed discussions and interviews on
soft engineering topics every 10 days
thanks to our audience and the partners
listed on our web site for supporting
the porkchop
[Music]
in contrast to some other episodes we
have two women and only one male person
on this episode and there is another
specialty and that is that we have two
Austrians and only one non Austrian so
we have this is very special apart from
that we're going to talk about aspect
orientation aspect oriented software
development a very female thing why
because there are a lot more women
dealing with with this topic than man I
think if you look at that at least the
percentage of women is higher than for
you know other topics in computer
science currently yeah I noticed that I
just wondered why this is the case but
listeners in case you wonder who whose
voice this boss so this was Krishna
shining or do you want to introduce
yourself briefly yeah my name is Krista
Shuang I'm working for Siemens and I'm
doing a little research also an aspect
oriented software development that's a
topic we in our research team have here
interested because of implications on
architecture is might have okay and the
other choice you might have heard
laughing in the beginning was iris Cole
so you maybe want to talk a little bit
about you briefly hi my name is Khoa and
I'm a PhD student at the university of
flint and i'm working here at siemens
i'm employed here as a PhD student and
the topic of my work is product line
engineering in connection to two aspect
oriented software development so both of
you have have quite some experience with
aspects and that's why we kind of
assembled in that group today just
before we get started want one more
comment we've had another episode where
we interviewed big okie chalice or
whatever he how-to whatever I don't
really have to pronounce his last name
chrysalis Alice whatever so that
was more of more or less an overview of
like opinions from the Guru
whereas this episode is well opinion
from the street yeah it's it's intended
as a real introduction to the topic so
we try to step through a OSD
systematically and not like we did last
time so if you if you haven't heard
kisailus interview yet you should first
listen to this one and then listen to
if we talk about aspect or inpatient and
then people often talk about separation
of concern we want to explain a little
bit what a concern is a concern is
anything somebody's interested in a
concern can be something the easier of a
system is interested in something the
developer is interested in or something
the person who's paying for software
development is interested in if you look
if you talk about AOP then people always
talk about the cross-cutting concerns
what's what's the cross-cutting thing
about it a cross-cutting concern is a
concern that cannot be easily cast into
one entity in the solution space so it's
not localizable it's not localizable
it's not per se cause it's not possible
to localize it is a concern possibly but
since there are some major concerns that
typically are functional concerns that
are mapped to the solution space first
and then there are some concerns you
know that come after this major concerns
such as such a security persistency
often they are non-functional concerns
typically you deal with the functional
concerns first and then you try to get
in the non-functional concerns and those
concerns then often cannot be
modularized that well anymore because
there is something already you did and
you have there and those concerns cross
cut the things that are there and
therefore a hard to modularize I don't
say that you can't modular eyes you know
security in some modules or subclasses
like authentication but nevertheless the
places where authentication and plays a
role in your software are many and not
only the authentication manager itself
so you say even although you might be
able to modularize
the algorithm that manages the
authentication calling that algorithm is
scattered through the system it sounds
to me a little bit that that's a
limitation of the underlying language I
mean object orientation has this one
decomposition hierarchy also called I
think the tyranny of the dominant
dominant decomposition so so so is AOP
to some extent a fix that that tries to
fix the shortcomings of object-oriented
programming
so I wouldn't say so that attorney after
Tom and I'm decomposition is just the
fact that you you start with some
functional concerns you want to model
arise and then you start decomposing
them in some way in an object-oriented
way for example and then some some other
concerns arise or there are
non-functional concerns you want to
modularize in addition and then those do
not fit well into the decomposition you
have chosen from the beginning and then
there are special effects called
scattering and tangling okay can you
explain what the difference between
those are I always mix them up so so
scattering is when one concern is
implemented in several modules so the
implementation of this one concern the
cross-cutting concern is scattered over
over many places of your object-oriented
hierarchy for example so and tangling
means that in one module of your
hierarchy there one module of your
hierarchy basically implements more than
than one concern so it's more or less
the same but looked at from a different
point of view either from the concern or
from you know one other motorized thing
in your solution space okay so I think
we agree that the whole point of a opie
and aspect oriented software development
is to come to the rescue here who to
help us get out of this this problem so
can you maybe very briefly like in two
or three sentences say what what aspects
do and what they are and then we can
look at the different like passwords
join point the point cut and all that
stuff so so an aspect is just a module
like like a class but that has a special
purpose and its purpose is to modularize
those so-called cross-cutting concerns
and an aspect can contain like a class
can contain members and operations but
special kinds of things should such as
point cuts and advices okay
so let's maybe define those terms and
then explain what they mean
first we probably have to explain that
you know when your mother arrives a
cross-cutting concern that doesn't mean
it's not cross-cutting anymore
a concern per se still Crosscut's the
rest of your system and that's why we
need some special you know means to to
make this aspect happen and those means
are for example point cuts that help you
defining there in your source code this
cross-cutting concerns interacts with
the rest of the system with a base
program yeah you can say base program or
primary concerns since it still is
cross-cutting you have to specify those
points where it cross cuts the rest of
the system and that's where this point
cuts come in to be able to specify a
point cut you first need a concept of
those points in your system you want to
interact with
that's called a join point so so let me
let me briefly try to say that in
different words in some sense I think a
point cut is a query over a running
program exactly you say you have some
points in your program you're interested
in that are called join points or points
worry join in the aspect and the point
cut picks all the points you're
interested in for one specific concern
or one specific part of the concern okay
so the other two terms are advice then
and the aspect itself so the aspect
itself is the module and the module
captures own members operations but also
point cuts and advices and the point
cuts as we already said select the
points where you want to add additional
functionality and this additional
functionality is then defined in the
advice so that's the additional things
you want to execute right that you apply
to the base program at places or well at
places that are selected by the point
cut that's right yeah so in a language
that's not aspect oriented the position
of the statement normally that reminds
when it's executed but in an aspect
oriented language is a bit different
because in the module you define
external to your base code where things
should happen and what should happen at
those
critics often say that that that to some
extent AOP is just a way of tweaking
code like you can do like bytecode
manipulation in Java but but what you
really do in really good aspect
languages is that you don't you don't
specify where something should happen
but rather when so a joint point is
isn't basically it's a piece or a place
in the execution of a program not a
source code location is that is that a
relevant distinction or is that more or
less picky no that's absolutely relevant
this distinction cause you're not
interested in you know changing your
source code to some extent but you're
interested in in points in the in the
control flow on your runtime of your
program for cert where certain
conditions are true and you want to be
you know as specific what these
conditions are as possible so typically
in aspect or in clean oriented language
that are used nowadays you you use
nevertheless lexical elements to specify
those points or norm structures a means
of defining that point let's make the
concrete if you want something to happen
after another method has executed then
this after method has executed is
basically that's a point in the
execution but a way of implementing that
thing is to do something in the code
exactly exactly and the the more
powerful your point cut language is the
easier it is to find the logical points
or to define the logical points in the
control flow of your application where
something should apply this can be
anything from you know do something when
a method is called up to do something
when my program goes into a specific
state and the state is a very
complicated thing that considers
historical information in your
application data flow information and
the application but every conceivable
and we'll talk about this joined point
model and the point cuts later in more
detail but to finish this discussion
about about the basics of it and there
are we already mentioned implicitly
something happens after before around
there are these different kinds of
advice that you want to lever a little
bit on the
in the aspect oriented language aspectj
that is maybe the most famous one and
that's pictorial it's an aspect oriented
language to this based on Java there are
three different kinds of advices so
there is the before advice that's code
that is executed before a point cut
matches then there is the after advice
that is executed after a certain point
could matches and there is the around
advice so the around advice can execute
code before as well as after or even
instead even instead that's right so and
and of course if you have an after
advice then India in the well you do
have access to the return value for
example if it's a method called so so if
the if the if the join pointer so let's
say if the point cut modifies the state
of something and of course in and after
advice you have access to that change
State yeah you can have access to it too
the whole context okay so so then let's
look at a couple of typical examples for
using aspect oriented programming
mm-hmm and there is the general
ubiquitous example of logging I guess
and then there is hopefully more more
useful stuff so um you provide a couple
of examples yeah so logging is the
typical hello world example like for
objects GUI objects whether you know
starting point for object-oriented
programming everybody could imagine that
a window and the button is an object
people had hard time to see that
something like like a symbol in a
compiler could be an object so this
changed in the last 20 years I think
still AO is in a stage where a lot of
people think you know logging is what
you can do with aspect orientation but
that's that's definitely not the case so
why is it that logging is this hello
world what's so simple about logging
that it's this kind of introductory
example if you do logging really simple
without thinking about it you could do
something like you know at every like
tracing at every entrance or exit of an
or a method you're right I entered this
method and I now leave this method again
for tip for real logging problems this
would be a lot too simplistic and we we
already had
is that no we don't want to use aspectj
for a login because if you want to have
meaningful outputs for logging you
rather you know write the logging
statement yeah
dedicated to the point where you want to
because that's the point if you do it
with an aspect what you do is of course
you factor out the logging functionality
system.out.print line something into the
aspect and then of course this aspect
needs to be generic in some way so that
you can reattach it to all these
different points and we had two for
example the one thing in an application
we wrote where we first wanted to use
aspects for logging we have the problem
that you know the logging output is not
meaningful at all cause you're not
interested in you know method exits and
entrances but you're interested in you
know something is accomplished now some
meaningful message and then you write an
aspect where you know you probably don't
the only thing you really encapsulate
there is the fact that you're logging
somewhere but for every point in your
source code you'd have a different
advice cause the message you want to
print is different so logging is
definitely not a very good example for
an aspect really tracing is different
tracing where you only want to know or
profiling or something like yeah it's
perfect
of course so and the trick is of course
that if you have an aspect then or if
you write an advice I should say then
you do have information to some meta
characteristic so you may be you know
you can you can ask the join point so
the join point object object is
typically represented as an object in
the advice you can query it what's the
name of the method I'm just entering
yeah so you have access to the metal
level to something and you of course
have information about the environment
of the point
you trapped yes ya know people know this
from from from other IT areas a trap is
something that fires if something
happens yeah and then we can get the
information about the calling object
typically about the caller about
parameters so if everything you might
interested in that that is relevant for
this one point and then you of course
can do things with those you can change
parameters and you can call other
methods from one of the two from the
caller or the colleague whatever is
necessary at that point okay so if
logging is not a good example and
tracing is very simplistic what then
what else can we say about typical
examples for AOP people often talk about
technical versus functional concerns so
that's true is it's often the case that
technical concerns are implemented as
aspects what is a technical concern
basically a non-functional concern what
is a non-functional concern a
non-functional concern that is is
something that that's not related to the
business domain okay
and that doesn't implement business
functionality
so examples includes security
persistence caching for example are also
consistent error handling is something
that's all often implemented as an
aspect so it's of course also possible
to to use aspects to implement business
concerns but to find a good example it's
always hard because it's hard to find a
good example for a business aspect as to
find one typical example for a business
object so it's also funny for example
one one one I think cross-cutting
business aspect could be billing so you
somehow look at the resources the
specific method works with for example
some kind of whatever may be three file
that you download whatever and and then
you you can weave a billing concern in
but the funny thing is that I have the
impression that as soon as things are
cross-cutting people are well but that's
not really business logic that's more or
less technical in our domain so we once
implemented a demonstrator that was
about a topological tree and we've
implemented the error propagation so
that's basically a tree of of hardware
nodes oh yeah all right so if one node
fails for example our reports and arrows
of this error is then propagated to to
top nodes and the propagation strategy
was something that we implemented as an
aspect
example and we could then easily
exchange between different propagation
strategies I mean the thing here is
again that when you think of typical
aspects then you think of things that
have been modularized or people try to
modularize before cause they're very
often had the problem that they had a
concern that should not pollute the rest
of the system when we look at you know
for example trade we component component
containers or even at coba services
they're interceptors yeah they're things
that you know all this polluted business
objects they were needed a lot like the
distinction between an application
domain and a software domain Yong Bosch
made this in one of his books and the
application domain has to do with your
business while the software domain is
something that's in the solution space
and we deal with such software domains
like persistency and databases like user
interfaces in so many different domains
that we know how to to handle them and
we know how to you know handle
persistency and therefore it's possible
or it was possible in component
containers already to to implement them
in a way such that they can be reused
for most business applications for
example it's interesting that you bring
this up because some people say well but
interceptors you know like a opion
framework level isn't really a ope
because it has been there all the time
the problem was there all the time so it
would be sad if I ap would have to
invent its own problems but the problem
of those cross-cutting concerns that
happen to be those software concerns is
therefore long and people had to solve
it and to make you know infrastructure
and business code reusable they had to
be dragged into their own modules that
were
and then to be services in that
container which is which is good and
great and nobody needs to call this
aspect oriented programs useful as long
as it's useful I mean aap has some
advantages about this since there is of
course some overhead when you have a
container and you intercept something
and then you look up what concerns or
what services should be applied at that
point this all takes time if you could
handle this with an aspect it's vovan at
compile time then a lot of runtime
overhead goes away to some extent you
could say that that's an implementation
detail that's an implementation detail
we'll talk about these details later by
the way yeah the other hand I mean it's
it's simply the concept so nobody would
modularize something only you know one
business case needs an opponent
container so you could buy such a
component container that offers you such
a concern it's all about about economics
only things that are used all over the
place would be fact without a container
exactly exactly and with aspects you
simply identify the things on your own
and implement them as aspects and have
all these mechanisms at hand it lets you
easily bring them together with your
race coach very good point
I think the next thing we need to
discuss is the joint point model so it's
basically the granularity of where you
can trap a program right so it seems
like the final of the joint point model
the more you can do with your aspect
language so the term power model seems
very important yeah the joint point
model is basically defines what you can
do with this aspect oriented language so
there are different approaches so there
are approaches that only allow you to to
basically intercept the public
interfaces of some components but there
are also languages that allow you to do
very fine-grained manipulation so it
depends on your needs so the more
fine-grained your endpoint model is the
more you can do with it but the more you
can do wrong of course as well yeah so
what you're saying is that there are
like the typical classical interceptor
frameworks such as korba where you can
only if a component is invoked
you can basically intercept that
invocation so how does
aspectek go further than that I mean
what kind of additional more
fine-grained time packs do you have
there
so in s picture there is also something
we didn't talk about yet that's
introductions so what you also can do in
a spec chase you you can introduce new
members or new operations into existing
classes and you can even change the
class hierarchy change a new super class
or something right so you can make
classes implement certain interfaces and
you can extend classes from others have
have classes extend from others that
didn't do it before so that's called
static cross-cutting okay because it
happens it changes the structure it
really changes the structure code it's
not just changing the code to simulate
intercepting some point in the execution
it really changes the code that's right
so it really changes the code and that
and I make things you can do in an
aspect chase for example you can there
are different join points such as method
calls or method execution so what's the
difference between the execution and the
call join point so the difference is the
context so in a call join point you're
at the caller side so you have access to
to the context of the caller who calls a
method right and with the execution join
point it's it's different so you're then
at the hall east side so you've access
to to the context of the one that's been
called okay so that's interesting
because if you have the classical
interceptor based thing and you
typically know it's basically an
execution point cut it's not as not so
easy to to find out about the Cawley of
a program because the typical
interceptor doesn't know where they come
from because you don't have that meta
information at the point where you call
if you do classical interceptors that's
right so in aspect Ju you've got both
things available
mhm there is other thing like object
creation object destruction variable
assignment right that's right so you can
also define point cuts that that select
certain constructor calls or also reach
accesses to certain variables or write
accesses to to set variables that are
useful I mean
I wonder whether it's good practice to
fiddle around with a running program on
that level level of detail or whether
you shouldn't say that you know like you
want to restrict the the interception
that an aspect does on on more
architectural level such as method calls
method execution it depends a lot on
what you want to do of course for many
systems it might be okay to tackle the
problem on the interface level you know
only being able to intercept public
interfaces for example but depending on
the cross-cutting concerns you need to
model arise it might make sense to be
more invasive you have to think of the
problem as being you know the
cross-cutting concern is in the source
code and even if you don't motorized it
it's still there
and you know there is there isn't a nice
article by great okie solace and mere
messini who talked about breaking
encapsulation you know yeah that's one
of these people criticize it breaks all
the nicely done encapsulation by hacking
around the details yeah but on the other
hand if the cross-cutting concern has to
be implemented in because it's tangled
with your place concern then it is
simply there and it breaks encapsulation
and why not modularize it and make it
obvious that it is there it might be
that you want to change it and fiddling
around in the code of your base concern
to change the cross-cutting concern is
not easy either
so rather have it motorized and have it
easily changeable if you need this if
you don't need it if you write a program
and you never touch it afterwards again
you probably it's not you know you don't
care unless it runs in tests what it
should you don't care about
modernization at all only if you want to
evolve it if you want to understand it
later on then you care about those
things it's a very good points or the
motivation for AOP is the ability to be
able to reuse either the base program
because it's now free of technical crap
or the aspect because you want to be
able to apply them to different program
program based programs this can be one
concern while you do it you can have
other concerns yes you can say
you want to you know evolve it and
understand it better what's in there
not only reuse it but you know only use
it in the context you have it but be
able to change it when you need to
change it for example or you could have
something like a cross-cutting concern
in a product family that varies yeah and
then you want to have two variations of
this one concern and you don't want to
have you know two variations of ten
classes only because this concern goes
through those ten classes but you'd
rather have two aspects and then you
exchange them also instead of having all
kinds of if thefts in the code or if if
this variant then else that's very in
bed and you can have different aspects
one per variant and either we've won or
we've the other two days ago we had a
visitor from the university of air
Langan la fin seeker showed an example
of the eCos operating system and there
is this operating system is highly
configurable it's more or less the
operating system family and he showed
one function there so it's implemented
in C++ and C even there's a lot of
conditional compilation in every you
know there are a lot of cross-cutting
concerns he showed one example of a
method and think that the method had 23
lines of code
only two lines of the code were the
business concerns and the rest
cross-cutting concerns always you know
is nice if this having such a thing
modularized really with aspects in this
example it's a spec C++ so all of
printing is the developer I don't know
he not alone yeah but he's kind of the
guy he's kind of the guy who is leading
this development and it looks a lot
nicer if he can't have those things
motorized you won't understand the base
code with all the if deaths easily and
it's a lot easier to have this aspect so
aspect or product line engineering
sounds like an interesting research
topic definitely we should do something
along that line so there is another
point cut that I always found a little
bit hard to understand at the beginning
and it's called flow C flow
what's that stuff so this point that
more or less takes the stack into
account so you can express something
like I want to do something at that
point when some other method from some
arbitrary other object was called before
so a look at the stack and the other
method was called before and I'm in the
control flow of this other method I want
to do something so it's really dynamic
that's not something you can easily do
with with static code weaving you really
really need to look during the runtime
of the program is this other method or
this other whatever method you typically
in the in the caustic of the current
execution path right right that's really
you dynamically find out if this
condition holds there are other things
you can do with aspectj
that you know can question other things
dynamically but see flow is it's one
typical thing you want to see there are
other things like data flow join points
for example other languages that
consider you know data item when the
data item was the same data item was
processed or the same object and you
might also be able to maybe said like
traps on if a specific variable gets
that value then yeah probably like this
or if a specific variable was operated
on with some other operation before
things like this so you can do a whole
lot of things there are research
languages like alpha is one of those
research languages that consider
everything that do a data flow and in
control flow analysis before the program
runs and when you even can take things
into account that predict what could
happen at some future time seen from the
point of time you are in an in your in
your program right now and then do
something bringing together all the
information you possibly can have about
your program could have calculated
before or at runtime so it's an
experimental language that's definitely
not very runtime efficient yes but it
gives a lot of room experimenting with
join point models
and with those kinds of point cuts okay
so I think there is another term we
night we need to discuss and that is
symmetric versus asymmetric AOP we often
talked about today about a base program
and an aspect and that's basically what
what a symmetric a always all about so
there's one there is one dedicated
mainly object oriented based program and
and an aspect that cross cuts many
places of your object-oriented hierarchy
so aspect a is a very famous example of
a language that's an asymmetrical
language and submit trick languages work
different so they implement all concerns
and separation no matter if they are
cross-cutting or not and at the end they
they get composed together so hyper
cherry was a very famous example say
wash their own so it's it's it's not
developed currently I think they stopped
it so they started a project called CME
concern manipulation environment which
is also one could argue that the a
symmetric symmetric AOP has kind of one
well I think it's it's much easier to
start with because the symmetric thing
requires a whole new way of thinking so
you you've developed software when you
when you develop software in an
object-oriented way you still do it when
you use a symmetric arrow languages you
just encapsulate your your cross-cutting
concerns as aspects and weave them back
in but if you use a symmetric language
you you have to think in in a completely
different way so you have to develop all
your concerns completely in isolation
and really think about how how to
compose them such a much more radical
approach is true since we're already
talking about the terminology there is
another pair of words which is a
heterogenous aspect versus homogeneous
aspect when you think of logging for
example which is a bad example the
already hooked up so let's say tracing
you do the same thing all over again you
more or less when you write an aspect
can
you know lift with one or two advices
and then nevertheless target a thousand
points in your program
and you do always the same thing that is
printing out the method name or the
parameters so this is quite homogeneous
I'd say so if you do the same thing at
many places
that's homogeneous then of course you
can have other kinds of cross-cutting
things a very good example for
explaining this is the subject observer
pattern so you have several subjects
probably in your object graph and you
have let's say one observer the logic of
the observer and the logic of recep
subjects that would be added by the
aspect is not the same so is
heterogeneous yeah so you have to do two
different things
advise the observer and advise different
logic to make this protocol happen and
that's called an a heterogeneous aspect
because it changes two different places
with different advice not to say that
there can't be you know a thousand
different classes that played a subject
but nevertheless you have
differentiation of things you do
different things at different places I
get the impression that many of the
typical technical concerns we talked
about are probably homogeneous and they
can easily easily be factored into your
library and apply to all kinds of
systems whereas some of the more
business-oriented functional aspects are
probably more heterogeneous probably I
myself would say I don't have enough
experience with this course I can
probably think of very homogeneous
business concerns they're very
heterogeneous infrastructure concerns so
it feels right but we can't prove it yet
probably in five years okay I can't get
a proper answer to do okay before we go
to the implementation technologies I
think one of the hallmarks of of AOP is
this thing called quantification which
is this query that selects a number of
points to do something which then goes
back to this model as homogeneous
homogeneous thing so I've heard people
say that that is the difference to some
of
other code tweaking approaches but that
only remark so let's look at
implementation technologies for for a o
P a T is important we will see why this
is important in a minute
so there are different ways of how this
interception of program behavior can
actually be made to work so in
connection to two AOP always talk about
something that's called weaving and
that's basically the mechanism how you
bring things together again because you
separate your cross-cutting concern in
an aspect but you have to get it back in
then again and weaving can be done on on
different levels and it's often called
weaving even if it's not really weaving
because you can also generate a proxy
for example but you could weave it at
different levels so you could weave your
source code you could weave some some
intermediate code such as as the
bytecode Java bytecode for example you
could also with your binaries there are
some research project that for example
bring a Oh even into the VM so the VM is
supporting AO then about all of these
approaches you just mentioned are what
you'd call static weaving because some
artifact by coding code source code is
actually changed that's true but but
when the VM for example supported it's
definitely dynamic so but in addition to
these two these static possibilities
there are also other ways for example I
know that small talk if you talk to
small talkers they think sometimes you
know aspect orientation isn't really
special because they've had more or less
metal object protocols for ages and they
could change the metaclass to implement
before and after behavior the same is
true for Cee Lo's for example that the
Lisp object system or even today in Ruby
where you can do a lot of these things
with with meta programming so there is
no changing of code in the sense that
code is manipulated but rather you
change the runtime system in some sense
that's also where ASD came from with
gray or catalyst for working on meta
object protocols the thing there is you
know you can do so many things and it's
not easy to to wrap your mind round
those languages and
changing more or less your languages at
runtime is not what the average
programmer does every day
well except if you're not every program
is a ruby program there's still you know
programmers to program in COBOL today
and they do not change the languages
usually I don't know there's an aspect
but nevertheless this aspect languages
try to bring this you know changes this
cross-cutting concerns in as you know a
deliberate programming model that helps
your mother solve a problem not arising
a cross-cutting concern and not changing
your program at run time or whatever
things you might want to do it's
dedicated for those want this one
purpose for this one area of problems
that's out there so that that's a good
point because people could say why do we
need a spec day for example you could
use the called bytecode engineering
library so tweet bye-bye to directly but
AOP gives you a well-defined programming
about not weakening the bite I mean you
can use whatever you can solve probably
any problem with any technology and and
fiddling around with whatever fancy
stuff you can think of the thing is that
that's not the way the majority of
software developers want to program you
want to think if you want to think in
you know base concerns and cross-cutting
concerns right away when having an
architecture and design in mind you
probably don't then want to think in
some byte code manipulations later on
but rather in some language constructs
with which you can develop what you what
you have in mind
there's also load time weaving happening
I think it's Java specific load time
leaving you can do with every language
that loads bytecode and you can
manipulate this pipeline either so to be
specific about this Java does not expect
J does not manipulate the Java source
code but the chavo bytecode and you need
not do this you know for all the
bytecode
but you could do this at load time of
each class basically lazily and for some
approaches like JBoss AOP it's quite
natural to leave in stuff at load time
and then make use of you know changing
aspects also at runtime so that's also
possible with some approaches like
tables AOP it's it can on if one hand be
a means to make the compile cycles short
like for respect J or on the other hand
it mean to be more dynamic more or less
not to decide in advance what aspects
should influence your basecoat another
way of implementing that stuff is then
also the probably the proxy and
interceptor patterns we want to go that
far so if you have an object that you
want to have aspects of by two or apply
it on and you can have a proxy for them
the property has a well way to insert
interceptors and then when you call you
call on the proxy the proxy delegates
but interceptors and that of course
there's only very coarse-grained because
the only thing you can intercept is the
public interface again that's again
something that's done in spring AOP for
example so there's an implementation for
Java and there's an implementation for
net using this and there is also an
implementation done by Microsoft people
by their patterns and practices group in
Microsoft that implemented such
framework we would call it a Opie
framework they say policy injection
application block because they at some
point politically decided that they
don't AOP right more or less or they
want to be you know they say that's an
early step in that direction and they
don't want to give the impression that
this is a fully fledged a opinion so
it's a transparent proxy approach so
every every object you want to intercept
you have to create using a factory and
then there is in between between this
proxy and the original object a series
of handlers and if each of these
handlers implements a cross-cutting
concern if you
the handler is kind of the interceptor
in the other terminology exactly okay so
let's look a little bit at the practical
experience of working with them with the
aspects one thing I think is that what
the AOP community talks about quite a
bit is that you can apply aspect after
the fact so you have your system it's
finished it does something and now after
you've finished it somebody comes up oh
we have to eat add this kind of
other feature to can add additional
features functionalities after the
system has been designed without
changing the system you just advise it
is that that realistic does that work I
mean it works of course you can do that
yeah but the question is is it good when
you do this more or less patching an
existing system I mean we don't want to
touch about people who are doing this
for some reason because there might be a
reason for this so you probably have a
third-party library and I want to to
change something there and you use
aspects you have to patch something or
you know things like this so they can be
valid reasons for doing this but in
general that's not really a good
practice to do this I'd say I'd rather
say say that you treat aspect as you
know first-class citizens and when you
see that there are cross-cutting
concerns and you have a good reason for
one in this concern not implemented
entangled in your system then you should
use aspects motorize it on the other
hand we talked about product lines so if
you have a cross-cutting feature for
example and you want to have different
variants of this features it's makes a
lot of sense to implement it in aspects
plus if you have a product family and
99% of your customers want to have the
system you know in a specific way with
only a few variations in it and then
there is this one customer who wants
something completely different you
probably don't want to pollute the rest
of your system or you know for this one
customer built
another variation in some complicated
way but rather more or less patched a
system for this one customer but what
you're saying is that in both of the
cases you just mentioned it's probably a
good idea to think about aspects when
building the system as opposed to
hacking the system afterwards so because
that's my impression too if you want to
use aspects well if you want to exploit
their potential then you need to think
of them as you develop the system as you
design the system just as you think of
object for example yeah absolutely
that's the best way to consider aspects
and of course then you Pia is not the
end so we should do something a always
before implementing something so if you
want to think in aspects we need aspects
before programming oh that's a good
point so what would that be I mean well
it sounds obvious of aspects and
analysis requirements but but what does
it mean specifically so if you can
implement aspects then it would of
course be nice to have a way at design
time when you probably paint some UML
diagrams to also be able to express that
there is an aspect there interacts with
the rest of the system and when you can
do this then you need modeling languages
that are more or less aspect aware so
that you can design your aspects in
architecture and design stage and then
of course when you want to think of
aspects early then at requirements
analysis time you should be aware of the
concept of an aspect you should not only
have in mind that you want to end up
with a clean object-oriented system
because that's what requirements
analysis see more or less bundle up your
your requirements to form entities later
on in your system and to keep in mind
that there are entities that can cross
cut other entities helps a lot if you
don't later on want to design and
implement all the aspects so so is a Oh
more of a mindset so because people
could say you know you can do a Oh with
normal oo if you use proxies and
interceptors and some of that stuff but
it's
important to think a a oh so that you
identify cross-cutting things and
modularize them with whatever means your
language gives you a Zao thinking more
important than a programming or whatever
I think it is yeah so I think it's it's
very important to just be aware of the
fact that there is something that's
cross-cutting that there is the effect
that that some concerns do not fit into
the decomposition you have chosen and
that you tried to to handle them in a
way that's that fits for your certain
problem and as we all know the language
you use guys you're thinking so if you
have a language that supports IO then
you might even that then you might start
thinking in a Oh whereas if you have
just an oo language it's not something
that comes easy to think in aspect so so
that made it so the point is that if you
have an AO language the chances that you
think an AO are higher than if you have
an oo language although you could also
do some AOH stuff in an O language and
it's true so if you use a language such
as aspectj for example it's it's very
likely that you as soon as you find out
okay there's something cross-cutting
that you try to model arise it as an
aspect term there are also aspects and
in modeling I mean I've heard Tom term
model weaving you could imagine aspects
that as we already talked about it at
all levels of artifacts so if you do for
example Mali weaving you would just
Express and an aspect that the modeling
level the same as for example in a
programming aspect oriented programming
language define point cuts in your model
and devices and then weave in the
elements so just the the join point
model is different but you would do the
same thing basically you would weave
elements into existing models and
gesture disclose the three of us are
currently working on a research project
that kind of looks at these things and
will maybe have a separate episode about
some of these more let's say weird or
advanced things later so we just wanted
to point this out there briefly go into
too much detail here before we look at
at at some a Oh tools at the end of this
of this episode or maybe at this second
part of a maybe double episode if I look
at the clock
one thing we need to discuss briefly are
I think compile-time aspects or
developmental aspects so so what is that
so that's something that's a very good
way of starting so you would then use a
spec sheet during development of your
application but you wouldn't have it in
your production code for example so you
could for example write an aspect that
gives you a compiler warning for all
your system.out.print lines you have in
your system so that's very easy to do
and it's very effective so you could
also check for certain architecture
constraints from for example prior
access direct access to private fields
from outside no stupid public fields
would write something like that or also
when you call for example your database
layer from your gooey layer that's
something you could could check for as
well and then have a compile error for
example if somebody would that's true so
you could do something like that and
that's a very good starting point for
people that use a spec Shea for the
first time so maybe they they fear of
having it in their production code so
they could just use it at development
time it also might be politically useful
if some operational department tells you
some operations Department tells you
that you cannot have this strange aspect
library in your system you don't have it
in the runtime system you just use it
during compilation that's true yeah I
wonder about one last thing and that is
if I have a number of aspects that each
maybe advise the same joint point how do
I I mean is there a way of finding out
in which although they apply I mean the
point is that if I if I separate out
stuff into aspects and then weave it
again then I think it that there is a
complexity involved in in trying to
imagine how it will be woven and what
the functionality will be what the
consequences are what the interactions
are how do you get that how do you
challenge or how do you manage that that
potential complexity so in general you
have to you know yet know yourself or
analyze yourself in which order the
aspects make sense for one joint
point if they're more than one the
target one join point but then in an in
the aspect language like an aspect J you
can express a partial order so if you
want to do you know tracing first or or
tracing last before probably some other
aspects changed the parameters then then
you can express a partial order so one
aspect then can dominate another which
means that this aspect has to be taken
first otherwise the ordering of the
aspects is what the compiler decides he
wants to do what's undefined it's more
or less undefined but you have means in
aspectj to do this by defining its
partial order and there are other aspect
language justice that allow you to
define more constraints on the ordering
like the compost our family what aspect
the compost our family of aspect
languages so that there is a lot of
research going on in aspect interference
so what in Floyd ten scan aspect have on
each other how do I analyze this and how
do I solve problems that might arise
from the interference of these aspects
so it's AOP a big research topic these
days it still is a big research topic in
[Music]
the states in europe and in asia there
are research communities everywhere
dealing with aspect-oriented software
developments are going beyond
programming there are for example two
big european commission funded projects
in europe that deal with this there are
more and more universities who have
researchers working on that topic and it
slowly comes also as a teaching topic
into the university so you know a lot of
students you already have aspect
oriented programming in some programming
course software engineering courses so
it's getting more and more popular and
it's possible to get people from the
universe
she's already who know about
aspect-oriented programming and how
relevant is it in in practice photo
developer in their real life projects
well I think there is a group of aspect
languages around frameworks like spring
or
chaebols the aspects are used but
without the customer knowing about the
aspects of things like caching or or
tracing or logging are implemented as
aspects in those frameworks anyway and
those frameworks also allow you to
define your own aspects and I think they
are quite popular the motivation for
aspectj is it's a little bit more you
have to do since you have to convince
somebody that you need a new compiler
and that's probably a little bit harder
if you have to convince your project
management so it I think s picture is
more currently used at this it groups
that are early adopters not that much
you know maturity but with the maturity
using frameworks like spring chaebols AP
and probably then also this policy
injection application block this
enterprise library where it's embedded
for them the barrier is quite low and I
think it's pretty popular there already
ok so before we wrap this up let's talk
a little bit about some of the tools
that are around we already mentioned a
couple of them so maybe let's start with
with a aspect a which is probably the
most well be the most complete and the
most sophisticated well more or less
implementation of AOP for Java right
that's true so it's it's maybe the most
famous one also so it's the embodiment
of i/o that's true so there is lots of
tool support for it so there is a nice
Eclipse plugin you've got lots of views
so you can even in your base program you
can you can
see in the Eclipse plugin if aspects
apply and if they do which aspects to
apply and you can go into your aspect
and you've got syntax highlighting and
all those things and and in case of a
spec J as Victoria is actually an aspect
oriented language we have new keywords I
guess we have a real new expression
language defining point cut that's a
language extension so to chava and
you-you-you need a compiler for that as
well and that's also because the very
fine-grained of joint point model
because it it happens on compiler level
it supports the the things we've already
talked about like method call join
points method execution things like that
spring AOP is different there right
that's true so spring AOP doesn't
require you to learn and you a new
language so it just generates proxies
and handles everything with in the
deployment descriptors that's true so
but in the new version it it also
includes the aspectj point cut syntax
but fundamentally the join point model
is still the public interface of a bean
that's true yeah and you can in the new
version select these point cuts by using
the aspect I using the aspectj point cut
language that's true something that I
heard was in aspect a 5 and also in
spring is that you can that you can
match you can point cut on on on
attributes on on top are five attributes
that's also seems very useful like if we
have that attribute on the method then
apply a kind of some kind of advice you
can do both things you you can use
introductions to even introduce new
annotations to two classes and methods
and also attributes and you can also in
in the point cut match then those those
annotations so if if a certain method is
is annotated with the special annotation
for example a synchronous then you want
to implement maybe an aspect that that
implements a synchronous method
invocation and then invokes this this
method as in Kronus lee so but to some
extent this is well a bit cheating isn't
it I mean if I have to annotate a method
with something in order for an aspect to
trap it I like this terminology then
then what's the point I mean I thought
the idea was to be able to
to to advice things from the outside
without changing the thing you want to
advise it's very useful if you have for
example a library of reusable aspects
and you take that library included into
your project and then just annotate
methods classes whatever with the
special annotations and then the
reasonable aspects of your library get
automatically applied at those points
mm-hmm so for such a thing that that's
very useful I see yeah so we talked
about aspect a a bit we talked about
spring AOP I think de Blasio P is very
similar to the spring AOP I guess in
that you can deploy interceptors on
component interface level right yeah
that's true yet okay so we don't need to
cover that too too much one thing I'd
like to cover before we really wrap up
is real or or less research in language
called C's LJ because I think it has a
couple of very interesting features
specifically it is it allows you to use
collaborations as aspects I think you've
worked with it so can you can you say
something about that yeah so Cesar Chase
is more advanced a ou language tend and
aspectj so it allows you to to define
collaborations so for example if if we
again think of the the subject observer
pattern if we would implement that in C
such a we would have different roles
like the role subject and the role
observer with the different operations
in it and then you can find those
collaborations to to an existing
applications that means that a
collaboration of a number of objects is
reified into its own type collaboration
is a type as opposed to classes just
being typed you can have a collaboration
yeah that's true and then and then of
course you can you can also also
specially specialize and possibly bind
those elements of this collaboration
right so you could have some base
application you find the subject role to
a certain class and you find the
observer role to a certain class and
then you can delegate the methods and
you you've got also that the same point
cuts available then in aspectj for
example so what do you don't have is
introductions but you don't need them
because you you implement this
functionality as the collaborations
basically
and and I also heard that that see such
a allows you to dynamically the boy
aspect in your program and undeploy them
again you can instantiate your
collaborations as you as you would
instantiate objects in an
object-oriented language and you can
deploy them and you can even under ploy
them at runtime them hmm that's
interesting because it it allows you so
applying an aspect is not something that
applies globally Europe and you define
it during compilation rather you can say
in that section of the code I want that
aspect to a to trap that the following
I'll show ya object okay any other old
language that we that we missed to talk
about maybe a couple of pointers to some
research languages there are languages
like arachnid that have features for
data flow point cuts their languages
like calm down which is an aspect
oriented component model but also next
to components has aspects or aspect
components that can more or less
intersect interfaces for other
components there are languages that
support distribution beyond what's
possible nowadays like remote point cuts
extensions to dotnet languages there are
other collaboration centric languages
like object teams so there is a whole
variety and you know extensions to a
whole lot of languages like Ruby like
small talk lots and lots of languages
have most of those languages are
research languages still universities of
course play around with language
extensions a lot really one of those
languages really jumps into the industry
because still nowadays there there are
not that many you know too many people
who are into this Vario experts who are
you experts and once there are a lot of
people right who are aware of those
aspects then I think there's a chance
for other aspect languages too
to be used in the industry to the usual
generation generational thing if you
want to have a big change in programming
philosophy takes a generation of
developers exactly it takes about 20
years and then so AOP is out there for
10 years now so they're probably another
10 years to go until they are common in
software development ok so if I haven't
forgotten anything really important then
let's wrap this up
thank you for listening and thank you
Krishna and iris for being on the show
and making this much more entertaining
than if the SD radio team had tried to
come up with that content themselves
Thanks Thank You Marcus thank you
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want more
information about the podcast and all
the other episodes visit our website at
se - radio dotnet if you want to support
us you can donate to the SU radio team
by on the website or you can advertise
for su radio for example by clicking on
the Digg reddit delicious and /not
buttons to contact the team leaves an
email to team and SI radio net or if
it's specific to an episode please use
the comments facility on the website so
other people can read and react to your
comments this episode of software
engineering radio as well as all other
episodes are licensed under Creative
Commons license please see the website
for details thanks to Charlie crowd and
the pot site music network for the music
used in this show the song is called
Vegas hard rock shuffle